Guide to the New-York Historical Society Printed Materials Collection circa 1800-1972 MS 3159
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society printed materials collection
circa 1800-1972
New-York Historical Society
MS 3159
350 Linear feet
An artifically created collection of printed materials curated and donated by a variety of individuals and institutions. Material includes newspapers and magazines, published books, invitations, pamphlets, certificates, illustrations, pamphlets, and other professionally printed items.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
TBD
Biographical / Historical
TBD
Immediate Source of Acquisition
TBD
Related Materials
TBD
Scope and Contents
TBD
Newspapers.; Magazines (periodicals).; Invitations.
- Chicago and New York City World's Fair pamphlets, 1933; 1964-1965 (Box NA)
  Scope and Contents
  1 box of material from the 1933 Chicago World's Fair and 3 boxes of pamphlets from the 1964-1965 New York City World's Fair.
- John Gemmill directories and newspapers, 1971-1974 (Box NA)
  1 box containing typescript lists of post offices and postmasters, directories, and newspapers.
- Harry P. Seeback newspapers, 1954-1966 (Box NA)
  An assortment of newspapers collected by Seeback. Includes the New York Times, New York Journal-American, and the New York Sunday News.
- Harper's Bazaar newspapers, 1874-1891 (Box NA)
  8 boxes containing issues of Harper's Bazaar weekly newspapers.
- Irwin Lutzky materials on folk music, 1952-1972 (Box NA)
  2 boxes and 4 envelopes containing programs and newspaper clippings regarding folk music and dancing.
- Mrs. Frederick W. Kobbe collection, 1914-1917 (Box NA)
  Books, pamphlets, programs, and clippings collected by Mrs. Frederick W. Kobbe.
- Harold F. Nutzhorn materials, circa 1740-1890, 1956 (Box NA)
  1 carton containing books, reports, and pamphlets. Many books and pamphlets are sermons and biographies from the 18th and 19th centuries. Also contains a Civil Defense Information Kit from 1956.
- John Bolos, Jr. calligraphy collection, circa 1978 (Box NA)
  1 box containing calligraphy transcripts, created by Bolos, of all the presidental inaugural speeches through 1978.
- American Waldensian Aid Society publications, 1917-1921 (Box NA)
  1 envelope containing invitations, programs, and pamphlets for the American Waldensian Aid Society.
- Gordon Gray family history papers, circa 1918-1969 (Box NA)
  1 box of printed material including the will and certificate of citizenship for Gray's father, Jacob Gerson; poetry; newspaper clippings; Yiddish theater programs; and literary journals containing Gray's work. Also contains some correspondence.
- J. Archer Turner drawing, 1943 (Box NA)
  1 envelope containing a composite drawing of work completed by the Turner Construction Company in 1942.
- James B. Wilbur materials, 1851-1955 (Box NA)
  1 box of published books and pamphlets regarding poetry, religion, America geography and history, collected by James B. Wilbur.
- Concert programs, circa 1860-1900 (Box NA)
  Concert programs for various performances throughout the United States in the late 19th century.
- Uniforms Worn in the War of the American Revolution (Box NA)
  1 envelope containing cards showing color illustrations of uniforms worn by soldiers during the Revolutionary War. Cards were published by the New-York Historical Society and have "For Sale Here" written beneath the drawings.
- Lenox Library Annual Reports, 1870-1894 (Box NA)
  2 volumes from John Stewart Kennedy's personal library.
- Richard Henry Greene published materials, circa 1881 (Box NA)
  3 envelopes of materials compiled by Greene including pamphlets of annual reports and various oration; a "New England Weekly Journal" page from 1728; and restaurant menus, advertisements, and ephemera.
- Freedom From Hunger articles, 1966-1972 (Box NA)
  2 boxes from the Food and Agriculture Organization's Freedom from Hunger program, containing newspaper clippings and pamphlets about poverty and hunger around the world.
- Russell C. Langdon newspapers, 1918-1919 (Box NA)
  1 box containing newspaper pages and clippings from the New York Times featuring photographs of soldiers and scenes from World War I.
- Steinway Hall Programme, 1886-1890 (Box NA)
  14 bound volumes of the Steinway Hall Programme.
- New York Times Mid-Week Pictorial War Extra, 1920 (Box NA)
  1 volume containing several issues of the New York Times Mid-Week Pictorial, all from 1920.
- New York City and Boston newspaper clippings, 1832-1899 (Box NA)
  1 box of loose New York and Boston newspapers, as well as many issues of "Harper's Weekly." Contains a handwritten list of contents.
- E. Marie Becker collection, circa 1945-1975 (Box NA)
  3 boxes containing material collected by Becker. Includes newspapers, magazines, pamphlets, some ephemera and memorabilia, handwritten copies of articles and letters written by Becker, membership directories of historical and library societies, and N-YHS annual reports.
- James Wright Brown programs and menus, 1915-1936 (Box NA)
  Folders of programs and menus from luncheons and banquets, as well as awards, nametags, and business cards. Organized by event name and contains an index.
- Fred Lockley newspaper collection, 1910-1939 (Box NA)
  6 boxes containing newspaper pages and clippings. Box 1 also contains one letter.
- Thomas Ollive Mabbott collection, 1859-1939 (Box NA)
  7 boxes and 2 envelopes containing business ad exhibition pamphlets, New York City postcards, theater programs, and cards.
- New York City fashion magazines, 1948, 1950 (Box NA)
  One issue eachs of "Flair" and "City of New York Golden Anniversary of Fashion" magazines.
- Charles van Ravenswaay historical publications, 1879-1955 (Box NA)
  Booklets and pamphlets on various historical topics, including the history of Manhattan Beach, Vikings on Cape Cod, typewriters, and doll houses.
- AAU Medical textbooks (Box 1 of 2), 1933-1955 (Box 1)
  Published books regarding various medical topics. Includes medical dictionaries and encyclopedias, as well as books on chemistry and drugs.
- AAU Medical textbooks (Box 2 of 2), 1933-1955 (Box 2)
- Ivan Nagel magazines, 1966-1969 (Box NA)
  Many volumes of "Playboy" magazine belonging to Ivan Nagel. Also some loose pages from the magazine.
- Social clubs local history, and literature publications, 1850-1972 (Box NA)
  Published books regarding various social clubs (1959-1972), history, and literature (circa 1850-1899).
- Frederick Jackson Turner political books, 1921-1968 (Box NA)
  19 volumes of books on politics.
- History of the United States by George Bancroff, 1886, 1931 (Box NA)
  6 volumes George Bancroff's "History of the United States," published in 1886. Also includes one In Memoriam program for Phebe Ketchum Thorne.
- Political documents on Andrew Jackson and James Madison, 1824, 1871 (Box NA)
  3 envelopes containing loose documents on politics.
- Trinity Church documents, circa 1850-1910 (Box NA)
  5 boxes and 1 envelope of pamphlets consisting of speeches and information about church affairs, finances, and administrative matters.
- Albert Ulmann research materials, circa 1940-1949 (Box NA)
  2 boxes and 1 envelope of Ulmann's compiled research consisting of newspaper clippings and other writings on New York's transportation, history, and various celebrations.
- William R. Lockman pamphlets, 1842-1928 (Box NA)
  9 boxes containing pamphlets and catalogs regarding US universities and colleges, religion, and politics.
- Mrs. Frank Rockwell collection, 1878-1955 (Box NA)
  23 published books on New York history and geography, as well as on some NYC social clubs.
- Mrs. B. Albert Stern songbooks, circa 1917 (Box NA)
  2 published songbooks, one missing a cover and one entitled "Twice 55 Plus Community Songs."
- Walt Whitman publications, circa 1935-1958 (Box NA)
  22 volumes and 2 envelopes containing published pamphlets and books regarding Walt Whitman.
- Samuel A. Cann pamphlets, circa 1918 (Box NA)
  3 pamphlets: 2 programs for the Fifth Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1918 and 1 bulletin for the Merchants and Bankerer's Business School.
- Cartoons by Homer C. Davenport, 1898 (Box NA)
  Published book of Homer C. Davenport's cartoons. Written on the inside cover is "Jane Elizabeth McClelland."